萝玛拉・嘉瑞
阿历克斯・哈赛尔
海莉・斯奎尔斯
帕帕・厄希度
艾米丽・伯林顿
杰弗里・斯特里特菲尔德
艾斯林・麦克古金
安雅・泰勒・乔伊
娃娃屋
第一季 第一集
根据杰西・伯顿原著小说改编
编剧 约翰・布朗洛
制片人 格辛・斯库菲尔德
执行制片人 凯特・辛克莱
导演 吉列尔莫・莫拉莱斯
阿姆斯特丹 1686年
你好
Hello...
约翰尼斯・布兰特
Johannes Brandt...?
这是要开动物园么
Are we to have a menagerie?
他的名字叫比波 是只长尾鹦鹉
Er... his name is Peebo. He's a Parakeet.
我是内拉 佩特内拉的缩写
I'm Nella. Short for Petronella.
你是管家吗
Are you the housekeeper?
约翰尼斯在哪里
Where is Johannes?
舍弟没有在家
My brother is not at home.
弟弟 那你就是
Your brother? So you are...
玛琳・布兰特
Marin Brandt.
奥托
Otto!
为您量足定做
For your feet...
奥托是舍弟的男仆
Otto is my brother's manservant.
这是女仆科妮莉亚
This is Cornelia, she is the maid.
他们会负责照顾你
They will look after you.
这是佩特内拉 庄园主的新婚妻子
This is Petronella. She is the Seigneur's new wife.
你一定想看看自己的卧房吧
I expect you'll want to see your bedroom.
拿到厨房去
To the kitchen.
他跟我一起住就行
Oh, he lives with erm...
来啊
Come on!
这里是我以前的卧房
This used to be my room.
不过这里的风景更好 所以归你了
But it had the better view, so we gave it to you.
千万别 您留着吧
But, no... please, you must keep it.
你误会了 我说的风景是你
No, you misunderstand. The view is of you.
阿姆斯特丹人必须要看到约翰尼斯・布兰特的新婚妻子
Amsterdammers must see that Johannes Brandt has a new wife.
宏伟的奥尔特曼家族传承祖宅
The Oortman's grand ancestral seat,
是不是既温暖又干燥
is it warm and dry?
没有特别宏伟 而且有些潮湿
It's not that grand. And it's damp.
我们负担不起堤坝的费用
We couldn't afford to maintain the dykes.
血统一文不值
Pedigree counts for nothing. Nothing.
没有堤坝 水就会漫涌而来
The dykes must be maintained, or the waters will rise.
我们派了第二好的船去接你 希望你不要介意
We sent the second-best barge. I hope you weren't offended.
约翰尼斯在用着第一好的船
Johannes was using the other one.
当然不会
No, of course not.
他知道我来了吗
Did he know I was coming?
你一定饿了
You must be hungry.
我让科妮莉亚给你送些吃的过来
I'll have Cornelia bring you something to eat.
这里有杏仁糖吗
Do you have any marzipan?
家里没有糖
We do not keep sugar in the house.
这种奢侈之物会腐蚀灵魂
The luxury of it sickens the soul.
科妮莉亚会给你拿些鲱鱼上来
Cornelia will bring you a herring.
精神点姑娘 他马上就要到了
Be still girl! He'll be here any moment!
听好了 我的女儿
Now you listen to me, my girl.
你必须要嫁给他
You need to marry him.
必须让他娶你 不然我们就完了
You need to make him want to marry you, otherwise we are ruined.
我倒是无所谓 但你的弟弟妹妹
For myself, I don't care. But for your brother and sister...
他来了 他来了
He's coming! He's coming!
阿森德尔夫特 三个月前
这是内拉 全名叫佩特内拉
And this is Nella... Petronella, I mean.
您的女儿十分美丽 奥尔特曼夫人
Your daughter is very beautiful, Madame Oortman.
您的负债具体有多少
How bad are the debts, exactly?
负债
The debts?
我知道您不止给我一个人写了信
I know I was not the only one you wrote to.
如果不是走投无路 您也不会这样做吧
You would not have done so had you not been desperate.
我说过她会弹鲁特琴吗
Did I mention she plays the lute?
赞美上帝 我们得救了
Praise God, we are saved.
他跟我提亲了
He has asked for your hand.
你觉得自己能爱上他吗
Do you think you could love him?
有什么区别吗
Does it make a difference?
没有 但是我想让你幸福
No. But I want you to be happy.
可能会吧
I think perhaps I could.
听说阿姆斯特丹人都会吃裹着金子的巧克力呢
I hear they eat chocolate wrapped in gold in Amsterdam!
都过来
Come, come.
她来了
She's here.
她到的时候你在就好了
It would have looked better if you'd been here when she arrived.
也许你该上去看看她
Perhaps you should go and see her.
让她睡吧
No, let her sleep.
你要理解  我很理解
-You have to understand... -I understand.
我得工作了 雷塞奇过来
I have to work. Rezecki, come.
庄园主从伦敦回来了
The Seigneur's arrived from London.
你要来一起吃早餐
You're to breakfast together.
来吧 我给你更衣
Come on, I'll dress you.
家母写信送来了我的尺寸
My mother sent my measurements over in a letter.
裁缝没有收到吗
Did the seamstress not get them?
尺寸是玛琳夫人送来的
Madame Marin sent them.
家母知道我的尺寸
My mother knows my size.
一定是哪里弄错了 我尽力吧
I'm sure it was a mistake. I'll do my best.
是没错 不过汉堡这个地方也不错
That's right although, Hamburg's a good choice...
还有马赛
And Marseilles...
早安
Good morning!
Good morning.
谢谢你 送我裙子
Thank you... for my dress.
裙子还有很多 不过
There are more. But...
这件有些大了
it's a little large.
玛琳 你觉得呢
Marin, don't you think?
算了 到时候改一下吧
Never mind, we'll have it altered.
过来吃点东西吧
Come and eat something.
今天吃素餐 来表现我们的谦卑
We are eating frugally today to demonstrate humility.
你是想说表现贫穷吧
Privation as thrill, you mean.
奥托 给我拿啤酒来 给内拉和玛琳也拿点过来
Otto, get me some beer. And Nella and Marin too.
我会消化不良的
It gives me indigestion.
你倒是继续目中无人啊
Go on, be defiant!
勇气是最近这个城市里最稀缺的货物了
Bravery is the rarest commodity in the city these days.
航行怎么样了
How was the voyage?
没什么可说的
Not much to tell.
伦巴第丝绸的进口权到谁手上了
The Lombardy silk, who won the import rights?
我忘了  快说
-I forget. -Who?
伦敦的亨利・菲尔德
Henry Field of London.
英国人 又是英国人
The English, always the English.
想想那个委员会 约翰尼斯
Think of the commission, Johannes.
我心里有数 玛琳
I know what I'm doing, Marin.
这间大房子还不够证明吗
This house is evidence enough, no?
你跟弗兰斯・密尔曼斯谈过他妻子的糖了吗
Have you spoken to Frans Meermans yet about his wife's sugar?
她在这儿等着我呢
So that's what this is about.
那些糖在仓库里放了一个月了
It's been sitting in the warehouse for a month.
你还是没告诉他你准备怎么处理
You still haven't told them what you plan to do with it.
我的姐姐认为糖会腐蚀灵魂 内拉
My sister thinks sugar rots the soul, Nella,
我每天卖这么多东西 她非盯上这一件
but of all the things I might sell, she pushes this.
你有什么看法呢
What do you make of that?
卖了那些糖
Sell the sugar!
不用你告诉我该怎么做
Don't tell me what to do!
你要去哪
Where are you going?
去看看你说的那些破糖
To check on your damned sugar!
我不相信你
I don't believe you.
你好
Hello!
这是约翰尼斯航行途中收集的吗
Did Johannes collect these on his travels?
整个世界蕴含在这一套盘子中
The world in a set of plates.
他这么富有 应该可以雇人替他航行吧
Isn't he rich enough to have someone travel for him?
庄园主的灵魂属于海洋
The Seigneur's spirit belongs on the seas.
他说陆地永远都比不上海洋
He says the ocean is something the land can never be.
每一滴海水都是独一无二的存在
No patch ever stays the same.
你们在干什么
What are you doing?
聊聊而已
Only talking.
他在工作 你看不见么
He's working. Can't you see?
这里不用管了 有些画卷要你去送
Leave that. There are scrolls you need to deliver.
玛琳 比波应该是想我了
Marin, I think Peebo misses me.
他需要呼吸一下新鲜空气 见见阳光
He needs fresh air and light.
他的活动范围仅限于这里
His place is down here.
可是约翰尼斯的狗就能
But Johannes's dog...
约翰尼斯是庄园主 他可以为所欲为
Johannes is the Seigneur. He may do as he pleases.
他一直都这么忙吗
Is he away a great deal?
没人逼你嫁给他
Nobody forced you to marry him.
希望你不会失望
I hope you are not disappointed.
我也没有想要办婚宴
I have no need of a wedding feast.
很高兴我娶到了你
I'm glad it's you.
约翰尼斯 我知道我们彼此还不了解
Johannes, I know we barely know each other.
但我保证 会努力成为一个好妻子
But I promise I will try to make you a good wife.
我也答应你 等你来到阿姆斯特丹
And I give you my word, when you come to Amsterdam
我会尽最大的努力 成为一个好丈夫
I will do everything I am able to be a good husband.
我在这个城里还有些急事
I have urgent business in the city.
不在这里过我们的洞房花烛夜吗
I thought you would want to spend our first night... here.
我也希望如此
I wish it were possible.
等你到了阿姆斯特丹
You'll come to Amsterdam and...
到时候再说
then...
约翰尼斯
Johannes...
我就想问一句 一会儿
I just wondered, will I
我还能不能
see you...
再见到你
later?
今晚
Tonight...
今晚不行
Tonight, I cannot.
那就尽快 好吗
Soon, then?
内拉 我之前说要尽最大努力
Nella, when I told you I would do everything in my power
成为一个好丈夫 我是认真的
to be a good husband to you, I meant it.
晚安 甜心
Goodnight, sweet girl.
亲爱的妈妈 我到阿姆斯特丹已经一个周多了
Dear Mama, I have now been in Amsterdam for over a week.
这座城市金碧辉煌 是我闻所未闻的地方
The city is a glory, like nothing I have ever experienced.
我的新家富丽堂皇 我也不要什么物质的东西
My new home is beautiful, and I want for no material thing.
正是这个男人 建造了这处房屋
... He is like a man which built a house
在坚石上打下了地基
and laid the foundations upon a rock.
-约翰尼斯的姐姐玛琳她...  -但倾听和行动的神
-Johannes's sister Marin is... -But he that heareth and doeth not,
-非常虔诚  -神是如此
-very godly, -he is like a man that...
-而且乐忠于控制我们的饮食  -就能凭空地
-and takes great interest in our diet. -without foundations,
在地球上建造了家园
built his house upon the earth.
至于约翰尼斯 他对我很好
As for Johannes, he treats me with great kindness,
不过他的工作非常忙
but his work takes him away a great deal.
我希望他能多陪陪我
I look forward to spending more time with him.
希望堤坝还完好无损
I hope the dykes are holding.
请将我的爱转达给
Please send my love to little...
别叫了 天哪
Be quiet! My God.
约翰尼斯 你干了什么
Johannes, what have you done?
怎么了 不是你告诉我去找个
What? You told me to find a...
找什么
A what?
给你的新婚礼物
A wedding gift. For you.
码头上有个人多出来一个柜子
A man at the docks had some cabinets left over.
我用龟甲和白蜡稍加镶嵌装饰了一下
I had it improved with tortoiseshells and pewter inlays.
可这是个什么
But what is it?
一所房子
A house.
你的房子 这座房子的微缩
Your house. This house.
多少钱  骨架两千
-How much? -The frame was two thousand.
算上窗帘和家具一共三千
Curtains and furnishings brought it to three.
三千荷兰盾
Three thousand guilders?
这是一个家庭好几年的生活费了
A family could live on that for years.
你有这么多闲钱 应该去捐给教堂
If you had money to spare you should have given it to the Church.
收起你的虔诚吧
Enough of your piety.
她不会喜欢的 我也不喜欢
Well she doesn't like it. Neither do I.
那你可太没有品味了
That's a bitch's taste for you.
你觉得呢 希望你能喜欢
What about you? I hoped you might like it.
我该怎么用这东西呢
What am I to do with it, exactly?
你自己想吧
You'll think of something.
干什么呢
What are you doing?
没什么 你的门开着
Nothing. Your door was open.
我想帮你关上
I thought you'd prefer it closed.
斯密特名单
Smit's List.
这是城里所有工匠和商人的注册名单
It's a register of all the crafts people and businesses in the city.
给我做什么
What for?
去装饰你的房子
To decorate your house.
舍弟会负担一切费用
My brother will pay for everything.
你不是说这是奢侈浪费吗
I thought you said it was an extravagance.
游手好闲者 恶魔上门来
The Devil finds work for idle hands.
登记表
娃娃屋工匠
Miniaturist.
斯密特名单
布鲁日著名钟表匠卢卡斯・温德布雷克之徒
Trained with the great Bruges clockmaker, Lucas Windelbreke.
在太阳标志之下
At the sign of the sun.
尊敬的阁下 我有一套九室的微缩房屋
Dear Sir, I have a house of nine rooms, on a miniature scale,
是放入陈列室的那种展品
that is to be displayed in a cabinet.
我有三个想添加的物品 等待您的回信
I venture three requests to you and await your response.
物品 一把带弦的鲁特琴
Item: one lute with strings.
物品 一个装得下鹦鹉的笼子
Item: one cage, suitable for a parakeet.
物品 一盒杏仁糖
Item: one box of marzipan.
卡尔弗尔街怎么去
How do I get to the Kalverstraat?
去那里干什么
What do you want there?
没什么 给人送封信
Nothing. To leave a message for someone.
给谁
Who?
一个工匠而已
A craftsman, that's all.
我和你一起去 夫人
I'll come with you, Madame.
不用了 我方向感很好
There's no need. I have a good sense of direction.
奥托为什么不来
Why didn't Otto come?
他不方便出门
It's not easy for him.
什么意思
What do you mean?
他是被一条葡萄牙奴隶船载来的
He was on a Portuguese slave ship.
当时十六岁 父母双亡
Sixteen years old. His parents were dead.
庄园主看到他 就将他带回了家
The Seigneur saw him, and bought him.
你说他是奴隶
You're saying he's a slave.
不 但他欠庄园主一条命
No.But he owes the Seigneur his life.
他刚进家门时 一个月都没说话
When he arrived, he didn't speak for a month.
他咖啡豆一般的肤色 我见过你偷看过他
That coffee-bean skin... I've seen you looking.
我没有  你当然有
-I do not. -Of course, you do.
谁都会看两眼
Everyone does.
杏仁糖 我们能不能
Oh, Marzipan! Do you think we could...?
不行 夫人
No, Madame.
小菊 你最近去哪儿了
Cornflower! Where've you been?
还等什么 快请进
Well, what you waiting for? Come in!
夫人 请四处瞧瞧
Please Madame, have a look around.
密尔曼斯夫妇坚持让庄园主当他们的经销商
The Meermans insisted the Seigneur distribute it.
他们知道 他能以更高的价格出口
They know he can get a better price abroad.
夫人完全赞成 虽然她不喜欢糖
And Madame's all for it, even though she hates sugar.
她和其他扫兴鬼都不喜欢糖
Her and all the rest of the killjoys!
我听说 他们要像禁止天主教徒一样禁止姜饼人
I heard a rumour they want to ban gingerbread men as papist...
简直荒谬至极
can you believe that?
夫人 想吃什么尽管尝
Madame, try anything you like.
干嘛不在本地卖 这里都快供不应求了
Why not sell it here? There's barely enough to go round.
很快就会来更多了
I think there's more going on.
更多 你什么意思
More? What would you mean...?
汉娜 你在干嘛
Hanna! What are you doing, woman?
我要走了 以后见 小菊
I must go. I'll see you soon, Cornflower.
就是这里
There it is.
太阳的标志
The sign of the sun.
以前从没注意到呢
I've never noticed that before...
你好
Hello?
有人在吗
夫人
Madame!
那里可没有人 夫人
I don't think there's anyone here, Madame.
橱柜去哪儿了
What happened to the cabinet?
不能放在门厅里 把光线都挡住了
It couldn't stay in the hallway. It was taking up all the light.
奥托 科妮莉亚 有人敲门
Otto, Cornelia, the door.
你好
Hello.
你在这做什么
What the hell are you doing here?
有个包裹 是寄给内拉・奥尔特曼的
A package. For Nella Oortman.
这是你的新婚妻子
So, this is your new wife?
我是杰克・菲利普斯 夫人
Jack Philips, Madame.
下回走佣人入口
Next time use the lower entrance.
他是谁 庄园主
Who was it, Seigneur?
没谁 奥托 没谁
No-one, Otto.No-one.
送货员而已
A delivery, that's all.
包裹里有什么
What is it that's in the parcel?
我为你送我的橱柜 添置了些小玩意
Just some things for the cabinet you bought me.
每个女人都是自己命运的建筑师
"Every woman is the architect of her own fortune."
物品 一把带弦的鲁特琴
Item, one lute with strings.
物品 一个装得下鹦鹉的笼子
Item: One cage, suitable for a parakeet.
物品 一盒杏仁糖
Item, one box of marzipan.
先生 感谢你按要求为我定制的物品
Sir, I thank you for the items I requested.
你的手艺非同一般
Your craftsmanship is exceptional.
然而我并未要求你制作一只摇篮
However, I made no request for a cradle,
我也不理解 你为何想送我一只摇篮
nor do I understand why you would wish to send one.
因此我将立刻终止交易
I must therefore curtail our transactions forthwith.
我诚心请求 佩特内拉・布兰特
Yours in good faith, Petronella Brandt.
又给那个工匠吗
For the craftsman again?
别打开
Don't open it.
不会的 夫人
No, Madame.
原来你在这 科妮莉亚去哪儿了
There you are. But where on earth is Cornelia?
你得开始准备了
You need to start getting ready.
准备什么
Ready? For what?
约翰尼斯打算带你去参加银器匠工会举办的宴会
Johannes is taking you to a feast at the Guild of Silversmiths.
窗帘怎么拉上了
Why are the curtains closed?
阳光太刺眼 仅此而已
The sunlight was too bright, that's all.
白天必须把窗帘全部拉开
We keep them open during the daylight.
否则路人会以为我们在隐瞒什么秘密
Otherwise people will think we have something to hide.
带我参加宴会
The feast.
是他的主意吗
Was it his idea?
我们一致认为带你去比较合适
We agreed it was appropriate you should attend.
你确定吗 那里依然没人
You're absolutely sure? There was no-one there again?
我从门底下塞进去的
I slipped it under the door.
汉娜向你问好
Hanna sends her greetings.
你美极了
You look wonderful.
玛琳 这条裙子掷下的重金是值得的
See, Marin, all that money I spent on dresses was worth it after all.
你为什么不来
Why aren't you coming?
带妻子出席更好 不是吗
I think it is better you're seen with your wife, don't you?
一定别忘了邀请密尔曼斯夫妇去吃晚餐
You must remember to invite the Meermans to dinner.
知道了 内拉 我们走吧
Alright. Nella, let's go.
感谢你 带上我
Thank you... for bringing me.
你没必要感谢我
You don't have to thank me.
那我应该感谢谁
Then whom should I thank?
你是我妻子
I mean, you're my wife.
无论我带你去哪 你都不必感谢我
You shouldn't have to thank me for taking you somewhere.
密尔曼斯夫妇也会到场吗
Will the Meermans be there?
玛琳似乎很期待 你将弗兰斯・密尔曼斯的糖卖出去
Marin seems very keen for you to sell Frans Meermans's sugar.
不是他的糖
It's not his.
是他妻子的
It's his wife's.
她将它视为实现梦想的手段
She sees it as a passport to what she's always wanted,
弗兰斯无法给予她的权势和地位
the power and position Frans couldn't give her,
但玛琳并不明白其中的复杂
but Marin doesn't understand the complications.
什么复杂
Which are?
他们一旦得到权势 就会失去控制
Exactly what he and Agnes will do with the power once they have it.
转过身去
Turn around.
闭上眼睛
Close your eyes.
只管微笑 不要说话
Smile, and don't say anything.
工会垄断贸易 制定价格
The Guilds have monopoly on trade, and set the prices.
不用理睬
Take no notice.
银器匠极为富有
The silversmiths' is one of the richest.
像我这样的商人 没有加入工会
For a merchant like me, who works outside the guilds,
出席不只是出于尊重 更是义务
attendance is not simply a mark of respect, but a duty.
给
Here.
你有没有想过 可以通过食物寻找本我
Did you ever think food is where we truly find ourselves?
看见了吗
See this?
新做的干酪中有孜然种子
Cumin seeds studding in new cheese
提醒着我可以开怀大笑
remind me I am capable of delight.
德尔夫特黄油 美味且多乳脂
Delft butter, so fine and creamy...
无花果
Figs
和酸奶油
and sour cream,
带我回到童年
taking me back to childhood,
是我现在唯一能记起的味道
only the taste of which I now remember.
你呢
You?
我母亲以前常把杏仁糖做成蛋卷
My mother used to make marzipan into rolls.
那味道从厨房飘来
And the smell coming from the kitchen...
让我心跳加速
it made my heart race.
比鲱鱼还好闻吗
Better than herrings?
你在海上吃什么
What do you eat out at sea?
吃人
Other men.
约翰尼斯 这边
Johannes! Over here!
谈生意 不会太久
Business. Won't be long.
我看布兰特挑选妻子的标准
I see Brandt keeps the same standard of wife
和他的行事风格一样
as he does everything else.
我是艾格尼丝・密尔曼斯 你叫佩特内拉对吗
Agnes Meermans. Petronella, isn't it?
现在告诉我 玛琳怎么找到你的
Now tell me, however did Marin find you?
玛琳 你什么意思
Marin? What do you mean?
约翰尼斯的新娘 她寻找了很久
A bride for Johannes. She's been searching for so long.
他们非常亲密 当然了 是姐弟的关系
They're so close, of course, brother and sister.
有时候我们在想 如果
Sometimes we wondered if...
艾格尼丝 拜托
Agnes, please...
弗兰斯 这位是佩特内拉・布兰特
Frans, this is Petronella Brandt.
我以为她是银器匠呢
Oh, I thought she was a silversmith.
约翰尼斯呢 我还以为有事要和他谈
Where's Johannes? I thought we were going to talk to him.
他来了
Here he comes.
密尔曼斯夫人
Madame Meermans.
大人 你今晚也用了平时的魔法啊
Seigneur. I see you are working your usual magic this evening.
没有魔法 夫人 只是我自己
No magic, Madame. Just me.
是糖的事 约翰尼斯
About the sugar, Johannes.
我还在找买家
I have it in hand.
我们从未怀疑过 只是
We never doubted. Only, er...
你觉得什么时候能卖出去
when will it sell, do you think?
获取最佳价格需要时间
To get the best price takes time.
鉴于东方的黑市
What with the black markets in the east,
和国内的背叛者 人们正在寻找好产品
and the adulterers at home, people are craving good product.
但我不会把你的糖带去交易所
But I will not take your sugar to the bourse.
交易大厅是个马戏团 市场被垄断了
The trading floor is a circus, the market rigged.
你打算卖到国外吗
You intend to sell it abroad?
我不久要坐船去威尼斯了
I sail to Venice shortly.
天主教徒吗
Papists?
当然 如果你乐意
Of course, if you prefer,
我们可以全扔去阿姆斯特丹
we could dump it all here in Amsterdam,
供大于求 只获得真实价值的四分之一利润
flood the market, and realize only a quarter of its true value.
如何选择完全在于你
The choice is entirely yours.
你是行家
You're the expert.
没错 我是
Yes, I am.
走吧 艾格尼丝 斯莱波特到了
Come, Agnes. There's Slabbaert.
我们应该去问候一下
We should say hello.
上帝与你同在
God be with you.
你也是
And you.
他们是谁
Who are they?
执法部门和船舶银行的官员
Schout and Schepenbank.
即阿姆斯特丹的法官和陪审团
Judge and jury here in Amsterdam.
他们为何那样看你
Why do they look at you like that?
因为他们无法掌控我
Because they don't control me.
他们想要掌控你吗
Do they want to? Control you?
不 他们想毁掉我
No. They want to destroy me.
大家很钦佩你
People admire you.
如果我不富有 你觉得他们会和我说话吗
Do you think they'd talk to me if I wasn't rich?
我们富有吗
Are we? Rich?
你抓不住财富的 内拉
You cannot hold wealth, Nella.
财富就像大海 试图紧紧抓住
It's like the sea. Try to hold on to it too tightly,
它只会如水般从手指间滑落
it'll slip through your fingers, like water.
玛琳总是很担心
Marin loves to worry.
你一定累了 去睡吧
You must be tired. Go to bed.
我不累 约翰尼斯
I'm not tired, Johannes.
但我得记下今晚见过的人
Still, I have to make notes on the men I met tonight.
你想要什么
What do you want?
你觉得呢 约翰尼斯
What do you think I want, Johannes?
我想成为你的妻子
I want to be your wife.
你是我妻子
You are my wife.
不 据我所知 我只是你的附属品
No. As far as I can tell I'm just... someone you own.
是对你有用的人 我只能如此猜测
Someone who's useful to you for purposes I can only guess at.
跟你的狗 跟奥托一样  内拉 拜托
-Like a dog, like Otto. -Nella, please...
我来这里十一天了 约翰尼斯
I've been here eleven days, Johannes.
比上帝创造世界的时间还长
Longer than it took God to make the world.
今晚之前 你几乎没跟我说过话
Until tonight, you've barely spoken to me.
你说得对 我很抱歉
You're right. I'm sorry.
我会补偿你的
I'll make it up to you.
过来
Come.
我有那么令你恶心吗
Do I disgust you that much?
你没有让我感到恶心
You do not disgust me.
你都不让我碰你
You cannot bear me to touch you.
不是那样的
It's not that.
我必须和她一起分享你 对吗
I have to share you with her. Is that it?
在我们其中一人
I think you'd better leave
说出后悔的话之前 你最好离开  不
-before one of us says something we both regret. -No,
不 约翰尼斯 我知道
no Johannes, I know...
给我滚
Go. Get out!
不要
Oh, no.
夫人 你不能整天躺在床上
Come on, Madame. You can't stay in bed all day.
玛琳夫人希望大家去教堂
Madame Marin wants us all to go to church
听佩里科恩牧师讲道
to hear Pastor Pellicorne preach.
桌上有寄给你的一些东西
And there's something for you.
一定出于工匠之手
It must be from the artisan.
反正是你订购的物件
Whatever it was you ordered.
可我没再订任何东西了
But I didn't order anything.
那就更应该看看里面有什么了
Well, then. All the more reason to find out what's inside.
看呐 他们带野蛮人过来了
Look! They brought the savage.
庄园主 密尔曼斯夫人
Seigneur, Madame Meermans.
令弟在哪
Where is your brother?
约翰尼斯有邀请你一同用餐吗
Did Johannes invite you to dine with us?
他并没有
No, he did not.
所以你们是要不请自来了
But you will come, won't you?
负责邀请的 不应该是他的妻子吗
Shouldn't his wife be the one who issues the invitation?
请务必明天过来
Please, do come tomorrow.
很荣幸受到邀请
We would be honoured.
请入座吧
Come, let us take our place.
通奸 高利贷 乱伦
Adultery! Usury! Fornication!
以及更邪恶的 无法面对上帝的行为
And fouler deeds, too degraded to name in God's house!
为何我要谈及所多玛和蛾摩拉的罪行(罪恶之地 源自《圣经》)
Do I talk of Sodom? Of Gomorrah!
不 我所说的罪行就在阿姆斯特丹
No, I speak of Amsterdam!
这个封闭的城市 无人见识个中罪孽
A city of closed doors, through which no man can see.
内拉 过来  但是上帝洞悉一切
-Nella! Please! -But God sees!
长久以来 我们一直忍受着同胞的罪恶
For too long we have tolerated the iniquities of our fellow men.
但是风暴即将到来
But a storm is coming.
所以让我们审视着自己的内心
So, look now into your own hearts
也审视着身边之人的内心
and the hearts of your neighbours,
好好反省自己犯下的罪孽
and consider how you have sinned.
玛琳 玛琳 你还好吧
Marin. Marin, are you quite well?
为人丈夫 要深爱自己的妻子
Husbands, love your wives...
只有两把
Only two of them...
你在干什么
What are you doing?
这些从哪里来的
Where did you get these?
娃娃屋
The Miniaturist.
我不知道工匠的名字
I don't know their name.
玛琳给我的斯密特名单上 只有这一家工匠
Marin gave me Smit's List. It was the only one in there.
你告诉他们什么了
What did you tell them?
什么都没说
Nothing.
但是你订制了这些娃娃
But you ordered these.
不 这不是我订制的
No. No, I didn't order these.
我只订制了鲁特琴 笼子和杏仁糖
I only ordered the lute, the cage and the marzipan.
这些娃娃 是自己送过来的
These just... came.
他们怎么知道照着谁的样子做
How did they know what to make?
我也不知道
I don't know.
不许再订了
No more.
不许再订了 听见了吗
No more, you understand?
我想你忘记了自己的身份
I think you're forgetting your place.
我什么身份
What is that?
仆人
As a servant.
我的身份是保护这座房子和里面的人 包括你
My place is to protect this house, and all in it, including you.
我们同生共死
We stand or fall together.
佩里科恩牧师周日的训诫真是精彩 对吧
A wonderful sermon from Pastor Pellicorne on Sunday, don't you think?
不过当然 约翰尼斯 你错过了
Oh, but of course, you missed it, Johannes.
让我猜猜他说了什么
Let me guess.
他将宽恕你们的罪孽
He offers absolution for your own sins,
但你必须要向身边之人告解
but only if you confess those of your neighbours.
我们来尝尝糖吧
Shall we try the sugar?
科妮莉亚
Cornelia?
我来吧
Allow me.
真是美妙
Exquisite.
科妮莉亚 奥托 你们觉得呢
Cornelia, Otto, what do you think?
非常美味 庄园主
Very good, Seigneur. Delicious.
感谢上帝 你要为我们狠狠赚上一笔了 布兰特
God be thanked, you're going to make our fortunes, Brandt!
你什么时候去威尼斯
When do you go to Venice?
一个月之内就动身
I'll be gone within the month.
一定要告诉我
I have to know.
布兰特给你了什么结婚礼物
What did Brandt get you for a wedding gift?
我也想要 而且要比她的好
I want one of my own. And I want mine to be better than hers.
感谢上帝 终于走了
Thank the Lord they've gone.
明天早上收拾好
Clear up in the morning.
这是黑貂毛皮吗
It's sable fur?
如果你同意的话  我为什么要
-If you had only consented... -Why should I...
亲爱的 我对你的爱如同变化莫测的海洋
"My darling, I love you like the ever-changing sea,
秋波荡漾 水波粼粼
always different, and always moving..."
你是穿越隔窗 温暖我身体的阳光
"You are sunlight through a window which I stand in, warmed.
一触即永恒
One touch lasts a thousand hours.
我对你的爱从心底一发不可收拾
I love you from the bottom of my heart..."
给我
Give it to me.
玛琳 对不起
Marin, I'm sorry.
我说
I said
把它给我
give it to me.
玛琳 玛琳 放开我
Marin, Marin, let go of me.
玛琳 你弄疼我了  滚
-Marin, you're hurting me! -Get out.
我会告诉约翰尼斯这件事的
Johannes will hear of this!
大家人呢
Where is everyone?
玛琳夫人身体不舒服
Madame Marin is unwell.
我把早餐端给她了 但她
I took her her breakfast, but she...
约翰尼斯去哪儿了
And Johannes?
他很早就去了办公室
He left early for his office.
不 告诉我 昨晚他去哪儿了
No! Tell me! Where did he go last night?
他没回家 为何玛琳如此担心
He didn't come back! And why is Marin so worried?
我说过了 他去了办公室
I told you. He went to his office.
不 不 你在撒谎
No. No, you're lying to me.
夫人 你要去哪儿
Where are you going, Madame?
现在还不到八点
It isn't even eight o'clock!
你应该待在家里
You should stay here.
我想去哪就去哪
I can go wherever I want.
奥托
Otto!
J・布兰特商行
约翰尼斯
Johannes?
不
No...
求你们走开 不
Please, go away, no...